Recently you have been speaking a lot
about the relationship between Chitta
and Mano the wild animal and the
trainer. Where and how does the body
kaya come in here and how would you
describe the fatter of sakaya in the
context of chitta and manu?
So where does the body come in? well
comes in by being there, by being your
outline, um being your backdrop,
um being your backdrop,
being the place where you find the
symptoms of your untamed mind.
Um agitations,
arousals, anxieties,
anxieties,
all of that's manifested in the body.
All of that's bound with the body. But
if you think that by observing body and
bodily sensations you're going to get to
the root of those symptoms that's that's
basically sending you completely on the
wrong track.
That's I say like hindrances are bodily
in a sense that hindrances are
inseparable from the body and they will
they will be manifesting in the body
those pressures. But if you think you're
going to find them in the body through
your observation,
as I said, you're already you're already
missing missing the missing the missing
the right direction because there's a
difference between uh
let's put it this way. There's a
difference between body being lived and
discerned passively
on the level of the background of your
experience and there is a difference
between you actively trying to observe
your body.
So whenever the Buddha is talking about
contemplation of the body, it's actually
always done in that passive indirect
manner because each time you try to
directly observe it, it becomes an
object of your experience. It becomes a
basically tactile sensations visual
basically become object of your senses
and that's not the body as the
sallayatana that's not the body that's
the these fields of six senses five
senses and the mind and that's what
people don't understand because of
course you have the body passively and
then you want to look at it and you
think you're looking at the same thing
but the fact is
you you're looking driven by your attention
you're looking driven by your attention
intention sorry intent and and attention
actually attention and intention to to
see the body on the as an object of your
senses uh makes it something else
makes it something that's actually not
your body there and then while you're
looking at it because the body or all
the other uh five senses are always the
negative are always that which cannot be
observed directly through the senses or
the other senses. So first and foremost
is the person has to learn to stop
trying to see the body,
observe the body. And that's that's why
the whole confusion of watching
sensations and contemporary techniques,
they think they're observing the body
the Buddha was talking about.
But they're not. They're just observing
the uh sense objects that they
mistakenly took to be that which their
body is there and then. So
So
body is that
which is always there which you can
always see with the corner of your eye
which you could always perceive these
things in that that that that are caused
by changes of mood hindrances and so on.
But if you try to grasp it directly,
attend to it directly, it won't be the
body you're looking at. Although you
might well delude yourself in believing
it is.
And what was the other question?
>> How you would describe the fet of sakaya
in the context of
>> chitta and manu.
>> Well, yeah, let's put it this way in
relation to what I just answered. So
imagine your entire life you are going
around driven by the sense objects
not just in terms of your uh passions
and desires that's obviously the fuel
but in terms of your views
see most people would think the body is
that which I observe not that which I
kind of peripherally quote unquote feel
or something. No it's what I can
measure. It's it's what I can see in
you, in him, in me and so on. So
basically through going around um
seeking and becoming dependent on the
level of the sense objects that's that's
where your consciousness gets
established. In other words, that's what
becomes a threshold for existence so to
speak. That's why I say for like a
really really untrained mind for that
person even their own thoughts are felt
like oh they're not real. what's really
long, it's only what's palpable, what
could be measured, seen, smelled, taste,
touched, and so on.
So, if somebody goes around like that,
unrestrained in those ways, the
threshold of their existence is
determined by these, as I said,
measurable things. Well, that pretty
much in and of itself
is where the sense of self is.
They put it out there. They assume it to
be out there in that physical material
world that I'm witnessing, that I'm
perceiving, that I'm engaging with. But
whether I do so or not, that matter
outside of me exists
and assuming the existence of anything
external to your five aggregates is the
core of atavvadaada.
So they might not people might not
necessarily think, oh, I exist
independent of this or I don't exist
independent of this. But the point is if
your mind is dependent on sense objects
past a certain threshold, you would have
perverted the picture sufficiently
enough that external uh the assumption
of external is where your actual being
is like nobody goes around thinking oh
I'm an annihilationist or I'm an
eternalist. But if you look at the views
where the emphasis is they will fall in
one of these two categories.
There is no third option. Well, the
third option is to be neither. But you
can't just figure that out. You can't
just figure out the middle ground
and then build from there. You need to
actually and actively withdraw yourself
from the dependence on the sense
objects. That's what gives you the the
the possibility of of of learning the
balance of the middle ground which is
the middle way which is then you could
truly say oh I I neither assume
everything is outside of me nor do I
assume everything is in me
but if a person tries to figure that out
before they would have actually tamed
their senses to some extent it's just
going to be another standpoint that's
going to fall back onto either too
external or a bit too internal.
So you want to figure it out, start
sense restraint, keep the virtue and
contain the mind. And as the mind
settles in as the taming starts taking
place, then you get to recognize your
assumption of the external existence as
gratuitous as it always was. You could
still have those thoughts, but they
won't carry the same weight as they do
for somebody who has been acting in a
unrestrained manner for so long. And
that weight is placed through the
emphasis of your desires and passions.
So it's kind of indirect. It's not like
um that desire immediately induces the
wrong view or something. But it keeps
you in that perverted state of what
comes first, what comes second, what's
actually more fundamental, what isn't,
and then your views will just naturally
start to grow. You have wrong views.
So atavvada is basically assuming
um
a standpoint. I won't even say assuming
yourself because again people think like
well I don't think about myself being no
just assuming a standpoint
in any direction that is assumed to be
external to your experience as a whole.
In other words, your experience as a
whole is placed second to the
standpoint. But that cannot be the case because
But that cannot be the case because
doesn't matter how objective your
standpoint is, it's still your
experience as a whole. So thinking the
outside of this experience as a whole is
yet another uh image, another experience
of your experience as a whole.
So you can't outrun it or outthink it or
step outside of it. You're always fully
confined within that.